Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- M
  - Murphy, James (Jim), Oct 19, 2007; cuid34662 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Mr. Murphy discusses a range of topics, beginning with his parents' background and his childhood in the 1960s and 1970s in Queens, New York. Murphy briefly describes his experience as a student at Our Lady of Lourdes, a Catholic grammar school in Queens. He discusses his education at Regis High School, a full scholarship Jesuit institution in Manhattan. During high school, he began an internship at WPIX (now the CW11), where he learned to write and produce news segments under such figures as Dan Doherty. Murphy explains that after high school graduation, he attended classes at Queens College, but he dropped out at the age of 19 to continue working full-time at the station.
    In 1981, Murphy moved to WABC where he became the producer of the Six O'Clock Eyewitness News with news anchor Roger Grimsby, who became one of Murphy's close friends. He also met Adrienne Barr at WABC, whom he would marry in 1986. Murphy relates that after he left WABC, he moved to WCBS, Channel 2, where he worked alongside his sister Mary, a street crime reporter at the time. Murphy then discusses his move to the syndicated film criticism program Siskel & Ebert & the Movies. Murphy describes how he and his new wife juggled their personal and professional lives after his move to Chicago. He explains that in 1993, he decided to return to New York City and to broadcast journalism because he missed the newsroom.
    Murphy discusses some of his experiences while working at CBS. He talks about the September 11th attacks on the World Trade Center and his experience working as executive producer for the Evening News in the days following the attack. He also discusses his involvement in the first network news broadcasts from Afghanistan after the fall of the Taliban. Murphy also explains how he helped CBS secure an important interview with former Israeli Prime Minister Ariel Sharon, during which Sharon announced a drastic policy change to break relations with former Palestinian President Yasser Arafat. Finally, Murphy highlights some of the bigger moments of his career, including the day he and Rather interviewed Saddam Hussein just weeks before the outbreak of the Iraq War in 2003. He describes the surreal circumstances when he met Saddam Hussein. Murphy also shares his conversation with Rather and Hussein following the interview, in which Hussein expressed his amazement with American political and media strategies. Finally, Murphy talks about returning to Iraq after the Americans began their occupation, and he describes the changing landscape of Iraq.
    Murphy then explains that he left CBS in 2005, following Dan Rather's departure. He talks about taking a job at ABC's Good Morning America in 2006, where he currently serves as the senior executive producer, working with anchorwoman Diane Sawyer. Murphy describes the personalities and professional capabilities of anchors such as Rather and Sawyer.
    In the course of the interview, Murphy elaborates on his personal life, discussing his Irish identity, his departure from the Church, and his family history, touching upon his father's isolated and abusive personality. He talks about visiting Ireland in the 1960s, the 1970s, and in more recent years. Murphy discusses how the economy in Ireland has transformed the country in the past few decades, and how the Celtic Tiger has affected his own family in Ireland. He reflects on the importance of his Irish identity but also on his tendency not to join Irish fraternal organizations.
    The small remainder of the interview focuses on his current job at Good Morning America. Murphy discusses the nature of morning news and his program's fierce competition with the Today Show.
    The Interview is 1 hour and 40 minutes long. Jim Murphy was interviewed on 19 October 2007 at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Sarah O'Hare and Linda Dowling Almeida.
    James (Jim) Murphy (b. 1960), senior executive producer of Good Morning America, ABC's morning news show, is the son of immigrants and the brother of television news reporter, Mary Murphy.
  - Murphy, Joseph, Feb 19, 2011; cuid34663 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Joseph Murphy (b. Millstreet, Co. Cork, 1931), a former columnist with the Irish Echo, is an active member of the County Cork Association of New York. His wife is Judy Murphy.
  - Murphy, Judy, Feb 19, 2011; cuid34664 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Judy Murphy (b. Ballinamore Bridge, Co. Galway, 1938) came to the United States from Rome, where she had been training to become a Franciscan nun. She left religious life and settled in New York in 1957 where she worked in banking. Her husband is Joe Murphy.
  - Murphy, Liam, May 29, 2008; cuid34665 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Murphy, Liam, 2014; cuid34823 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_26)
    Liam Murphy was born in Lubbock, Texas in 1943. He grew up in Irvington, Pennsylvania and graduated from the Virginia Military Institute in Lexington, Virginia.
    This interview was conducted by Danielle Zach on September 29 and December 15, 2014 at the State University of New York Maritime College in the Bronx, New York. The interview covers Liam Murphy's early life in Irvington, New Jersey and his interest in Ireland during his childhood. Murphy recounts his father's term as mayor of Irvington in the 1940s. He discusses his membership in the Ancient Order of the Hibernians.
  - Murphy, Mary, Nov 14, 2008; cuid34666 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Mary Murphy (b. 1959), Emmy-award winning television reporter, currently the weekend anchor of the CW11 News at Ten (New York) and correspondent for the "Fact Finders", a crime investigative team consisting of herself and fellow reporter Peter Thorne on the CW-11, is the daughter of immigrants and the brother of Jim Murphy, senior executive producer of Good Morning America.
  - Murphy, Maureen, Oct 23, 2008; cuid34667 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Murphy, Sr. Regina, Nov 9, 2007; cuid34668 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Sister Regina Murphy discusses many aspects of her life, beginning with her parents' immigration to America and her childhood in Riverdale, New York. She details the occupations her parents held as new arrivals in America – her mother a live-in maid and her father a clerk in a grocery store. When her parents wed her father quickly bought out a grocery store, and her mother stopped domestic work and assisted in the store.
    Sister Regina Murphy reviews her childhood – she received religious education throughout her life, attending St. Margaret's School in Riverdale for primary education, New York, Sacred Heart of Mary High School, and two years at Marymount College in Tarrytown before she entered the convent. She stresses that her religious education during those formative years greatly influence her decision to enter the convent.
    Sister Regina Murphy discusses her decision to enter the convent, against the wishes of her parents. Four years earlier, her older brother Tommy joined the brothers. He would leave before taking final vows, but at the time she entered the convent in 1959, he was still with the brothers. She declares that the only time she remembers her father using profanity was when she told him she wanted to enter the convent. In a similarly vehement reaction, her mother tore up her acceptance letter to the Sisters of Charity, and it was only upon further inquiry with the order that Sister Regina Murphy learned she had been accepted. Although her parents did not initially accept her vocation, Sister Regina Murphy says she felt truly called to enter the convent. She recalls that she was especially stirred at the prospect of doing missionary work.
    Sr. Murphy describes her first foreign mission was to the Bahamas. She worked in education, but during her tenure, she noticed the stark difference between the lives of the native poor and the tourists who visited the Bahamas. This started her personal quest for a better understanding of social justice principles. She talks about her appointment as Mission Coordinator for the order, and how she was able to visit missions in Guatemala. She recalls meeting with a fellow sister named Barbara Ann Ford, who was influential in creating water projects in the poor villages and who participated in The Recovery of Historical Memory project organized by Bishop Juan Geraldi to collect the stories of the survivors and victims of the civil war in Guatemala. Part of the project included providing mental health service for those who were affected by the rampant violence and crime that accompanied the war. Sr. Barbara was shot and killed in 2001 under suspicious circumstance, however her work in Guatemala helped many and also influenced Sister Regina Murphy.
    She describes how her experiences in the Bahamas and Guatemala along with the coming of Vatican II sparked an awakening in her. She saw the changes enacted as part of Vatican II as an energizing and necessary force in the Church. It seemed to her that religious work evolved from seeking to help individuals on a day to day basis to fixing the societal infrastructure responsible for basic injustices. These realizations propelled Sister Regina Murphy to become involved in justice, peace, and corporate responsibility projects.
    When advocating for corporate responsibility, Sister Regina Murphy describes her integral role in the implementation of the McBride Principles and the enactment of the Fair Employment Act in Northern Ireland in 1988. As part of the Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, she traveled to Northern Ireland in the hopes of getting factories to sign onto the McBride Principles. She recalls that the ICCR was successful in obtaining the signatures of fifty companies. While Sister Regina Murphy was in one General Motors Factory in Northern Ireland, she talks about how her presence caused a temporary strike and shutdown of the factory. Although she was not dressed in a traditional habit, workers guessed that she was a Catholic nun. Seeing her discuss workplace issues with managers in the factory upset the predominately Protestant workers, inciting them to walk off the job. Despite this fervor against the McBride Principles, it was her support, along with that of the ICCR, that she says helped to pass the Fair Employment Act.
    Sister Murphy talks about the current state of vocations in the Church and what she sees for the future of the convent. She describes her life today as a religious woman – what it means to her and what her Irish identity means. She ends the interview talking about her job as property manager for the order, acting as general contractor on major construction projects for the order
    This oral history with Sister Regina Murphy was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview took place on 9 November 2007 at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Julia Ryan and Linda Dowling Almeida. The interview is 2 hours, 47 minutes long, on 2 CDs and had been logged at ten minute intervals.
    Sr. Regina Murphy (b. 1939), the property manager for the Sisters of Charity of New York and an advocate for corporate responsibility, fought hard to establish the McBride Principles.
- N
  - Naughton, Frank, Mar 18, 2011; cuid34669 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Frank Naughton (b. Manhattan, New York, 1939), a Professor and former Chairperson of Sociology at Kean University in New Jersey, was President of the New York Irish History Roundtable. His father was raised in Cahir, Co. Tipperary from age 6 to 19.
  - Neal, Richard E., 2016; cuid34824 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_94)
    Richard E. Neal was born in 1949 in Worcester, Massachusetts and was raised in Springfield. He received his bachelor's degree from International American College in Springfield in 1972 and his master's degree from the University of Hartford in Hartford, Connecticut in 1976. He was elected mayor of Springfield in 1984, serving until his election to the House of Representatives in 1988. At the time of the 2016 interview he was the ranking member of the Ways and Means Committee, a co-chairman of the New England Congressional Caucus, and the Democratic Leader of the Friends of Ireland Caucus.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at Richard E. Neal's office in Springfield, Massachusetts on May 2, 2016. The interview covers Neal's early life and his political career. Neal describes his family and his difficult home life. He discusses his entry into politics, his election as mayor of Springfield in 1984, and his election to the House of Representatives in 1988. He discusses his involvement in peace negotiations in Northern Ireland in the 1980s and 1990s and his work with Representative Thomas P. "Tip" O'Neill and Senator Edward M. Kennedy in this work. He also discusses his involvement in immigration reform in the United States, particularly on behalf of Irish immigrants and the history of the Irish in Massachusetts.
  - Nolan, Mary B., Mar 8, 2012; cuid34670 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    Mary B. Nolan (b. Kilfinny, Co. Limerick, Ireland, 1937) is a long-time resident of Brooklyn who became involved in many Irish organizations after emigrating to New York City in 1953.
- O
  - O'Brien, Cathleen, 2014; cuid34825 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_13)
    Cathleen O'Brien was born in 1955 in New Rochelle, New York and was raised on Long Island. She was a member of Irish Northern Aid Committee (NORAID).
    This interview was conducted by Danielle Zach in the Riverdale neighborhood of the Bronx, New York on July 1, 2014. The interview covers Cathleen O'Brien's childhood and her political activities. O'Brien discusses her childhood, the importance of Irish cultural activities in her family, and the participation of her parents and grandparents in Irish and Irish American organizations, including Clan na Gael, Friends of Irish Freedom, and Irish Northern Aid Committee (NORAID). She recounts becoming aware of Irish republican issues, becoming involved in NORAID, and hosting an annual commemoration of the events of Bloody Sunday in 1972. She also discusses the 1981 hunger strike in Northern Ireland and the acquittal of George Harrison in 1982.
  - O'Brien, Jack, Mar 22, 2011; cuid34671 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Jack O'Brien (b. Hoboken, New Jersey, 1928) played fife for the Jefferson Street Hoboken Playground Band, New York World's Fair Champions in 1939. In 2002 he was inducted into the New Jersey Drum Corps Hall of Fame. He has also taught classes at New York University's Tisch School of the Arts.
  - O'Brien, Jack, 2014; cuid34826 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_24)
    Jack O'Brien was born in Washington, D.C. in 1938. He graduated from McKinley High School in Washington. He joined the United States Army after high school and served in the Korean War. He left the Army in 1967 and served in the Army Reserves for the next 12 years.
    This interview was conducted by Danielle Zach on September 9, 2014 at New York University's Glucksman Ireland House in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Jack O'Brien's early life in Washington, D.C. and the significance of Irish culture in his life. He recounts how his experiences in the United States Army aided his work representing labor unions in Washington and his involvement with the Irish Republican Information Services in Dublin, Ireland.
  - O'Callaghan, Anne, 2015; cuid34827 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_54)
    Anne O'Callaghan was born in 1942 in Ballybay, County Monaghan, Ireland. She graduated from St. Louis Secondary School in Monaghan. She immigrated to the United States, settling in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania in 1970. She married Sean O'Callaghan in 1971.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll on April 17, 2015 at the offices of John O'Malley and Associates in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The interview contains Anne O'Callaghan's family ancestry and her early education. She recounts the story of her immigration to the United States,and her work at the Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania. She describes meeting and marrying Sean O'Callaghan and having three children. Callaghan recounts her involvement with the Irish Immigration Center in Philadelphia and her work with Tom Counihan to establish the original board of directors in 1998.
  - O'Callaghan, Patricia, Nov 2, 2007; cuid34672 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Ms. O'Callaghan discusses a variety of topics beginning with her family and childhood in Cork, Ireland and what life was like growing up on a farm. After obtaining a Bachelor of Arts in English, French and Sociology at the University of County Cork, she moved to Dublin to pursue a Higher Diploma in Education at Trinity College. In Dublin she was given the chance to teach inner-city kids, a far cry from the one room school house she attended as a child. She describes returning to Cork to work for Cork Local Radio as a news presenter. Wanderlust led her to answer an ad in the newspaper for a job marketing Irish hand-crafts in San Francisco, California. Ms. O'Callaghan was handed an H-3 Visa to live in what describes as a fantasy life in the United States, an experience that was somewhat different from the lives of the people she helped later in life.
    She talks about how she turned a temporary stay into a permanent move after she left California for New York to work as a flight attendant for Transamerica Airlines. Reintegrating the Irish back into her life, she became involved with Adrian Flannelly's Irish radio talk show. She describes how the growing number of undocumented Irish in the mid-1980s led Adrian Flannelly to discuss solutions with the Archdiocese of New York. The talks led to the formation of Project Irish Outreach within the Catholic Charities division of the archdiocese, under the supervision of Monsignor James Murray.
    Asked to help with the project's establishment, Ms. O'Callaghan found a real purpose in helping the undocumented. She wrote a small booklet titled Immigrating USA: A Guide for Irish Immigrants to answer immigrants frequently-asked questions. Project Irish Outreach had a great impact on Ms. O'Callaghan and the Irish community and she discusses at length the work that the project was able to do through community outreach, immigration and social services, and partaking in efforts to inform people of their rights. The program became a social worker network in a number of fields.
    She recalls the mobilization of the Irish American community along with various other social service and legal organizations during the 1980s, also noting the always positive attitude that Americans, especially New Yorkers, have had towards the Irish.
    While discussing the way her position and role within Catholic Charities has diversified and evolved, Ms. O'Callaghan explains the transformation of Project Irish Outreach since its establishment in 1987. She expresses the many ways in which immigration and the immigrants themselves have changed over time, including the complexity of the immigration system and the choices available to immigrants and emigrants. She delves into the hurdles that the undocumented and documented have to face and the ways the immigration system and legislation can evolve to fit the needs of the immigrant population.
    She closes with describing the strength of the Irish community and the people that have affected her life through her work and what her Catholic and Irish identities mean to her.
    Patricia O'Callaghan was interviewed on 2 November 2007 at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Katie Hiebert, Linda Dowling Almeida, and Joe Ready. This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 1 hour, 41 minutes long, on two CDs and had been logged at ten minute intervals.
    Patricia O'Callaghan (b. 1951 Cork City, Ireland). She emigrated to San Francisco and has become an advocate for immigratant rights. She has run Project Irish Outreach for 20 years.
  - O'Cearna, Micael, 2014; cuid34828 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_5)
    Micael O'Cearna was born in 1920 on Great Blasket Island, County Kerry, Ireland.
    These interviews were conducted on April 3, 2014 by Miriam Nyhan and on May 1, 2014 by Siobhra Aiken. The interviews were conducted at Micael O'Cearna's home in East Longmeadow, Massachusetts. Both of the interviews were conducted in Irish.
  - O'Connor, Patricia Young, May 21, 2011; cuid34673 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Patricia Young O'Connor (b. Co. Cork, 1928) became President of the Cork Ladies' Auxiliary of New York in 1960 and served as their delegate to the United Irish Counties Association and to the St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee. She owned a bookstore in Sheepshead Bay, Brooklyn and worked for the Board of Education at Beach Channel High School until retirement.
  - O'Donnell, Lisa, 2015; cuid34829 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_48)
    Lisa O'Donnell was born in 1986 in County Galway, Ireland. She received her bachelor's degree from Galway-Mayo Institute of Technology in Galway in the 2000s and received her master's degree from Central Saint Martins in London, England in 2011.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll in Amherst, Massachusetts on April 10, 2015. The interview covers Lisa O'Donnell's family, education, and career as an artist. O'Donnell describes her family members, her education, and her interest in the arts. She discusses her love of drawing as a child, her realization as a teenager that she could become an artist. She discusses her experiences and teachers at Galway-Mayo Institute of Technology (GMIT) in the 2000s. She describes relationships she developed with her instructors and other students at GMIT and her decision to immigrate to England. She discusses her influences, her working methods, and projects on which she was working at the time of the interview. She describes pieces of her work to O'Carroll and the inspiration behind them.
  - O'Donoghue, Clare, Oct 10, 2013; cuid34674 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    Clare O'Donoghue (b. Clonmel, Co. Tipperary, Ireland, 1960) worked as a banker in Ireland, came to Boston in 1992 on a Donnelly visa and works in the health sector.
  - O'Donoghue, Margaret, Jul 8, 2011; cuid34675 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Margaret O'Donoghue (b. Limerick City, Ireland, 1960), a psychotherapist and an adjunct professor at the New York University School of Social Work, emigrated to America in 1982 and is raising two children in New Jersey.
  - O'Donoghue, Myra, 2015; cuid34830 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_49)
    Myra O'Donoghue was born in 1966 in Clonmel, County Tipperary, Ireland. She received her bachelor's degree from University College Cork in 1988. She received her doctorate from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1998.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania on April 15, 2015. The interview covers Myra O'Donoghue's early life in Ireland and her working life in the United States (US). O'Donoghue describes her family and recounts memories from her childhood in Ireland. She discusses her interest in the sciences and her experiences in college. She discusses spending the summer of 1988 in Boston, Massachusetts and her decision to remain in the US. She discusses her decision to apply to doctorate programs in chemistry in 1993 and describes her experiences at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology between 1994 and 1998. She describes the type of work she has done between 1998 to the time of the interview and recounts her experiences as a woman in the chemistry field.
  - O'Donoghue, Noreen Lydon, Jan 22, 2011; cuid34676 (Box 3, Folder 28)